בוקר טוב. Boker tov. Today's דף daf is מ"ט mem-tet and keeping
with the fact that we were just discussing the יובל, yovel, 49.
Ha ha. Okay, anyway. Yes,
so we're on the last line of מח עמוד ב mem-chet amud
bet and we started a new פרק perek which is מפני תיקון
עולם, mipnei tikkun olam, although here it's sort of bringing us into
a very different realm, like a whole חושן משפט choshen mishpat collecting
of debts and different תיקון עולם tikkun olam in terms of which
type of creditors and people to whom money is owed can collect
from what type of property. And just to quickly say the first
point of the משנה, mishnah, dividing a three-way division, somebody who has
been damaged—has had property or a person damaged—can collect from the עידית,
idit, from the top grade property. We're talking about real estate. Let's
call them A, B, and C for future reference to make things
easier. Can collect from grade A real estate of the damager. Somebody
who has... is a creditor who has lent money can collect from
the grade B property, real estate. And a woman for her כתובה
kesuvah can collect from the grade C. And there's a תיקון עולם
tikkun olam sort of logic in all of those. So the obvious
one that we're focusing on now is the person who's been damaged
and the תיקון עולם tikkun olam is you want the damager to
pay of the most quality property, the highest grade A property, to
help them be more careful, less negligent, and so on in terms
of inflicting injury or allowing injury to occur to another person. Now
the גמרא's Gemara question is, is that that's not actually a תיקון
עולם tikkun olam of the rabbis? That's actually in the verse. It
says מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם meitav sadeihu umeitav karmo yeshaleim when
somebody's animal goes and grazes in somebody else's field. So the גמרא
Gemara says, well this is according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael who
would say that from the תורה's Torah perspective it means the best
of the fields of the ניזק, nizak, of the damagee, and the
תיקון עולם tikkun olam is establishing that it's the best of the
fields of the מזיק. mazik. So the גמרא Gemara is trying to
figure out what that means, the best of the fields of the
ניזק. nizak. First it thought it meant, and then it rejected, that
that meant if your animal consumed one acre of my grade C
property, you'd have to pay for an acre of my grade A
property. That of course doesn't make any sense. So now the גמרא
Gemara is coming on to conclude what this does mean for רבי
ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael at a תורה Torah law perspective, and then what
the rabbis added at a תיקון עולם tikkun olam level. So, last
line of מח עמוד ב. mem-chet amud bet. אלא אמר רב אחא
בר יעקב, Ella amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, says רב אחא בר
יעקב: Rav Acha bar Yaakov: הכא במאי עסקינן? Hacha bemai as'kinan? What
are we talking about? כגון שהייתה עידית דניזק כזיבורית דמזיק. kigon shehayesa
idit de-nizak k-ziboris de-mazik. Now the general question here: are we rating
A, B, and C subjectively or based on some universal standards rating?
Okay, we'll worry about that later. Let's not let that confuse us
right now. But let's just assume, say, that the best property of
the ניזק nizak is equal to the worst property of the מזיק.
mazik. So basically if I'm the damagee, okay, my best quality property
is grade C. You're the מזיק. mazik. You've got grade A, grade
B, grade C. My property at most it gets up to grade
C. Right? Some of it's even, maybe even worse, D, E, F,
who knows what? Okay. So if we said that you have to
pay with, that I can collect from, from the best, but the
best is measured based on my property which is grade C, I'd
only be entitled to collect from your grade C property because that's
the best of mine. Now the amount I collect is equal to
the amount of damage. So let's say the damage is equal to
one acre of grade C, and let's just assume for simplicity's sake
that every next level is twice as good as the previous one.
Okay, so you damaged one acre of my grade C property. If
we defined that the property I collect from you is based on
my best property which is grade C, I'd collect one acre of
your grade C property. But if I'm collecting from your best property,
grade A, well then I get a quarter-acre of your grade A,
okay, which is equal to the same amount as a full acre
of my grade C. Which do I collect? So that's what the
גמרא Gemara says: כגון שהייתה עידית דניזק כזיבורית דמזיק. kigon shehayesa idit
de-nizak k-ziboris de-mazik. The best property of the
ניזק nizak was like the worst of the מזיק. mazik. Okay, could
have said the middle of the מזיק, mazik, doesn't matter. רבי ישמעאל
סבר בניזק שיימינן. Rabbi Yishmael savar binizak shaminin. When it says you
have to pay, the best of the field, it means I collect
from the highest quality of my field. I collect from your grade
C property because my best property is grade C. And then תיקון
עולם tikkun olam is to collect from the best. Right, exactly. רבי
עקיבא סבר בדמזיק שיימינן. Rabbi Akiva savar bidamazik shaminin. No, no, no.
You get to collect the best property of the damager. So I
get to collect your grade A property. It would only be a
quarter of an acre, but I get to collect your grade A
property. Now that's the obvious תיקון עולם tikkun olam because, because you
cannot make the מזיק mazik pay, meaning give higher quality than he's
got, right? I can't, I mean, we're not going to force you
to go out and buy property so I can collect from it.
Just give me the cash. Okay. So the best, the thing that
punishes you the most and entitle, you know, you the מזיק mazik
the most, and entitles me the ניזק nizak the most, the thing
that is that you have to pay from the best of yours.
the property, that's the most we can make you do, right? That's
the so therefore rather than determining the quality of the property that
I can collect from, the grade of the property based on what's
best for me, we're going to punish you more, we're going to
give me more and punish you more and let me collect from
the best that you've got, okay? So that's תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam.
And that for Rabbi Akiva there I mean for Rabbi Ishmael the
תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam was מן התורה-ly min ha-Torah just to collect
from my from the best of the damagee and the תיקון עולם
Tikkun Olam is I get to collect from the best of the
damager. Right according to Rabbi Akiva's תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. Oh there's
no תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam for Rabbi Akiva. Okay it's only for
Rabbi Ishmael. Okay. I'm sorry then the משנה's Mishnah according to Rabbi
Ishmael. That's what the גמרא Gemara said. Okay. So okay. Now מאי
טעמא ד Mai Tama D' so that's the best we can do
for תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is the best of the damager, right?
That's the most we can make that guy or the best quality
we can make that guy pay is the best quality that he's
got. So let's say yours was your best was like a grade
D. Am I, you know, what if there's like a complete mismatch?
Right, so in that case if your best, well okay, then it
gets to a whole question about do we do it based on
universal standards or based on whatever, but bottom line is there's no
way even if my best was I'm the damagee my best is
grade A and your best is grade C there's no way we
can make you pay grade A, you don't have grade A. So
okay, so therefore the best we can do for me is say
you've got I can collect from your best property and that's what
Rabbi Ishmael says is the תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam. Rabbi Akiva says
right and that guy get two acres. Rabbi Akiva says or for
Rabbi Akiva says that's already the הלכה Halachah according to the תורה.
Torah. Okay. So מאי טעמא דרבי ישמעאל? Mai Tama DeRabbi Yishmael? נאמר
Ne'emar the verse says שדה Sadeh למטה lematah it says כי יבער
איש שדה או כרם Ki yavar ish sadeh o karem
when your animal consumes a field, which means your animal consumed in
my field, and נאמר ve-ne'emar שדה למעלה sadeh lemalah I mean it
actually says pay the best of the field, but it says it
consumed the field. So the field it was consuming was my field,
was the field of the damagee. So when it says pay the
best of the field, it means the best of the field of
the damagee. Okay? It said field twice, the first time it was
talking about the damagee so the second time it's talking about the
damagee. נאמר שדה למטה ונאמר שדה למעלה מה שדה האמור למעלה דניזק
Ne'emar sadeh lematah ve-ne'emar sadeh lemalah mah sadeh ha-amur lemalah de-nizak
the same way the field that's being damaged is the one of
the damagee, אף שדה האמור למטה דניזק af sadeh ha-amur lematah de-nizak
when it says you pay the best field, it means of the
damagee. Okay, that's how he says it means that's what the verse
means of the damagee. רבי עקיבא סבר Rabbi Akiva savar מיטב שדהו
ישלם. Meitav sadehu yeshalem.
No, it says he shall pay the best of his field. So
since the he paying is the damager, the his field is the
damager. Okay, that's just consistent in terms of the pronoun here or
of the subject. דהאי דקמשלם, De-hai de-kamashalem,
the field of the one who's doing the paying. Okay, ורבי ישמעאל
ve-Rabbi Yishmael what would Rabbi Ishmael say? הני גזירה שוה והני קרא.
Hani gezeirah shavah ve-hani kra. The גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah does its
job and the simple sense of the פסוק pasuk does its job.
הני גזירה שוה לחדא מן Hani gezeirah shavah le-chada man the גזירה
שוה gezeirah shavah does its job to like we said that you
determine it by the best field of the damagee. So now what
do you do with the simple sense of the verse that sounds
like it's the damager's field, the best damager's field? והני קרא דאית
ליה למזיק עידית וזיבורית וזיבורית דידיה לא שויא כעידית דניזק דמשלם ליה
ממיטב. Ve-hani kra de-it leh le-mazik idit ve-ziborit ve-ziborit didey lo shaveya
ke-idit de-nizak de-mashalem leh mi-meitav.
Let's say you don't have a whole range of choices, okay? Let's
say your animal damaged my grade B field and you've got grade
A and grade C. Now I am entitled to collect according to
Rabbi Ishmael grade B, right? You damaged my or my best, I
don't care what you damaged, my best is grade B. So I'm
the damagee, I'm entitled to collect grade B. Okay, that's my best
field. But you have A and C. Which one do I do?
Do I have to go down to C or can I go
up to A? So that's why the פסוק pasuk says מיטב שדהו
meitav sadehu there are times we will go up to your best
field, because we're not going to force me to give up what
I'm entitled to. So if I can't get what I'm entitled to,
I get an upgrade and I get to get your grade A.
Okay? So Rabbi Ishmael says and what do you do for תיקון
עולם Tikkun Olam for that case? There's no תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam.
So Rabbi Ishmael says the פסוק pasuk says you basically start with
the best field of the ניזק Nizak of the damagee, but if
that's not available in the מזיק's Mazik possession, you're entitled to go
up to the next grade of the מזיק Mazik and that's the
מיטב שדהו Meitav Sadehu of the מזיק. Mazik. Okay, so let's just
read that again. הני גזירה שוה לחדא מן Hani gezeirah shavah le-chada
man that you start with the best field of the damagee. הני
קרא דאית ליה למזיק עידית וזיבורית Hani kra de-it leh le-mazik idit
ve-ziborit if he has A and C, the damager, וזיבורית דידיה לא
שויא כעידית דניזק ve-ziborit didey lo shaveya ke-idit de-nizak and the grade
C of the damager is not equal to the best of the
ניזק Nizak of the damagee, to what the ניזק's Nizak entitled. So
if the ניזק Nizak can't get what he's entitled to because the
מזיק Mazik doesn't have it, so then דמשלם ליה ממיטב de-mashalem leh
mi-meitav he's able to get an upgrade and go to the next
higher quality that the מזיק Mazik has. Alright? So that's how Rabbi
Ishmael says it. But there are times even in that case maybe
since you don't have a grade B I'm going to go to
a grade A minus with you and Rabbi Akiva would still say
I'm going to let you go to the grade A or the...
grade A plus or the triple A or whatever it is, right?
So anyway, according to רבי ישמעאל, Rabbi Yishmael, you're basically still limited
to the best of your field, of the ניזק's nizak field, but
you're allowed to go up a level if you have to to
get the most you know the the next the quality that that
is equal to or greater than you know what as close to
the value the the best of your field. Whereas רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva lets you just collect from the absolute best that the מזיק
mazik has, which is obviously a much better way of getting people
to control their animals and be careful if they're gonna have to
give up their absolute best property. Unless I'm misunderstanding this, I felt
like but at the end of the day, whether you say it's
on the Torah level or rabbinic level, both they both agree, right?
Once you have the רבנן תיקון עולם, rabbanan tikkun olam, then everybody
agrees. I'm talking at the דאורייתא d'oraissa level. Right. At the end
of the day now when you have the תיקון עולם tikkun olam
of the משנה, Mishna, everybody agrees that you get to go to
the absolute prime real estate that the מזיק mazik has. Okay. So
I went ahead and I you know my animal grazed in your
swampland and you're going to collect from me some like you know
prime Manhattan real estate. Okay now it's not going to be worth
more than the actual damage. Okay but nevertheless I don't want to
give anybody my prime real estate, right? Okay you know like I
was saying to somebody else I think it was David I sent
you the other day well what difference does it make? It's all
worth the same. It's a big difference as we know. You could
have a house in a bad neighborhood that has a market an
official market price but good luck trying to offload it. Right. So
it makes a huge difference what quality of land you're talking about.
All right so now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay. רבי עקיבא אומר לא בא הכתוב אלא לגבות לניזוקין מן העידית
וקל וחומר להקדש. Rabbi Akiva omer lo ba hakasuv ella ligbos l'nizikin
min ha-iddis v'kal v'chomer l'hektesh. Now we're going to finish up the
sort of quote about this before we get back to the תיקון
עולם. tikkun olam. So רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says that the Torah
here is giving you the right to collect from the best of
the מזיק. mazik. Okay the grade A of the מזיק mazik and
certainly הקדש. hektesh. So what does it mean certainly הקדש? hektesh? So
the גמרא Gemara says מאי קל וחומר להקדש? mai kal v'chomer l'hektesh?
What does it mean הקדש? hektesh? So the simple sense is when
הקדש hektesh gets to collect if you damaged הקדש's hektesh property הקדש
hektesh gets to collect from you from your best property right? Makes
sense הקדש hektesh should have more you know better rights more privileges.
אילימא דנגחיה תורא דידן לתורא דהקדש, Ilei'ma d'nagchei tor didan l'tor d'hektesh,
let's say one of our oxen gored an ox belonging to הקדש.
hektesh. So we have now pay from the best of our property
to pay back הקדש. hektesh. שור רעהו אמר רחמנא ולא שור של
הקדש. shorei re'ehu amar Rachmana v'lo shorei shel hektesh. It says כי
יגח שור איש את שור רעהו. ki yigach ish shor ish shorei
re'ehu. If the שור shor of a man gores the שור shor
of his fellow then you know then he has to pay. Okay.
So the point is that this isn't the ox of his fellow
it's the ox of הקדש. hektesh. It's not owned by a normal
person. So therefore you should be exempt right? There's obviously like one
of the best אבן עזראs Ibn Ezra on the Torah is he
quotes somebody who is it? בן זוטא Ben Zuta or some some
Karaite who says that שור רעהו shorei re'ehu means gored his fellow
ox. So not the ox of your fellow but his fellow ox
like his friend ox. So אבן עזרא Ibn Ezra says אין לשור
ריע אלא בן זוטא בלבד. ein l'shor re'a ella Ben Zuta bilvad.
The only friend an ox has is this בן זוטא Ben Zuta
guy. Okay anyway so okay but anyway so שור רעהו אמר רחמנא
ולא שור של הקדש. shorei re'ehu amar Rachmana v'lo shorei shel hektesh.
So you don't have to pay anything. You're only obligated if it's
a person's ox. אלא לאומר Ella l'omer
okay
well let's take a look. No well let's take a look. אלא
לאומר הרי עלי מנה לבדק הבית. Ella l'omer harei alay maneh l'bedek
habayis.
Okay that you basically you know make a donation to the בית
המקדש Beis Hamikdash for a hundred dollars. מנה Maneh is more like
I don't know a thousand ten thousand dollars. Anyway דאתי גזבר ושקל
מעידית. d'asi gizbar v'shakal m'iddis. So when the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash
comes to collect the debts owed to it it can collect from
your grade A real estate. So the גמרא Gemara says one minute
לא יהא אלא בעל חוב ובעל חוב דינו בבינונית. lo yehei ella
ba'al chov u'ba'al chov dino b'veinonis. What's the קל וחומר? kal v'chomer?
That doesn't make הקדש hektesh קל וחומר kal v'chomer is הקדש hektesh
should be at least as entitled but not that הקדש hektesh should
be better. Where would we have a basis to say that when
the הקדש hektesh acts as a creditor when הקדש hektesh comes to
collect a standard debt that they're entitled to grade A? A normal
creditor for a loan for a debt is entitled to grade B.
Why should הקדש hektesh get more? Right? A we have no basis
for saying it and no a קל וחומר kal v'chomer doesn't say
that the other thing is more. A קל וחומר kal v'chomer says
the other thing is equal. At least. Okay but not more. קל
וחומר kal v'chomer is if it's true by this it's certainly true
by that. Okay so we have no basis to say קל וחומר
kal v'chomer means it's an equal treatment and we have no basis
to say that הקדש hektesh should be more entitled when it's coming
to just סתם stam collect debts than any normal person. Okay so
how so that can't be what it means. Anyway we weren't even
talking about debts we were talking about damages. וכי תימא קסבר רבי
עקיבא בעל חוב שקל מעידית כניזקין, V'chi teima kasavar Rabbi Akiva ba'al
chov shakal b'iddis k'nizikin, maybe רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva happens to be
of the opinion that a normal creditor collects from grade A and
he's saying hey if a creditor collects from grade A like he
does by damage then the same would also be true by הקדש.
hektesh. But one minute איכא למיפרך ika l'mifrach you can challenge this.
מה לבעל חוב שכן יפה כחו בניזקין תאמר בהקדש שכן הורע כחו
בניזקין. Mah l'ba'al chov sheken yafeh kocho b'nizikin tomar b'hektesh sheken hora
kocho b'nizikin. You can't even make a קל וחומר kal v'chomer you
can't even argue that הקדש hektesh should be as good
you can't even argue that it should be equal because הקדש hektesh
is worse. weaker than a normal person. How do I know הקדש
Hekdesh is weaker than a normal person? Because I just told you,
הקדש Hekdesh doesn't get to collect for damages done to it. So
what type of a קל וחומר Kal Vachomer exists? הקדש Hekdesh is
in a weaker position when it comes to collecting debts than normal
people. They can't collect for damages done to its property. So how
can you even make a קל וחומר? Kal Vachomer? So we can't
be talking about נזק Nezek because it doesn't... הקדש Hekdesh doesn't collect.
We can't be talking about other things because number one, other things
are probably just grade B. Even if other things are grade A,
we have lost our ability to make a קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer.
So what are we talking about? The house never loses. What all
right. וכי תימא, Vechi Teima, we have to prove it though. וכי
תימא קסבר רבי... Vechi Teima Kasavar Rabbi... I've just said that. שכן
הורע כוחו בנזיקין. Shekein Horah Kocho BiNezikin. לעולם דנזקי תורי דנזקי תורי
דהקדש. Leolam Dinazkei Torei Dinazkei Torei DiHekdesh. Let's go back to a
נזק Nezek case, which is the פשט Pshat of what we're talking
about, damages. Okay, our ox gored הקדש'ס Hekdesh's ox. So how is
הקדש Hekdesh collecting? רבי עקיבא סבר לה כרבי שמעון בן מנסיא. Rabbi
Akiva Savar Lah KeRabbi Shimon Ben Menasya. He holds like רבי שמעון
בן מנסיא. Rabbi Shimon Ben Menasya. דתניא, Detanya, we learned in a
ברייתא: Beraisa: רבי שמעון בן מנסיא אומר: Rabbi Shimon Ben Menasya Omer:
שור של הקדש שנגח לשור של הדיוט פטור. Shor Shel Hekdesh Shenagach
LeShor Shel Hedyot Patur. If הקדש'ס Hekdesh's ox gores a layperson's ox,
you don't pay anything. ושל הדיוט שנגח לשור של הקדש, Veshel Hedyot
Shenagach LeShor Shel Hekdesh, but if an ox owned by a normal
person gores an ox owned by הקדש, Hekdesh, בין תם בין מועד
משלם נזק שלם. Bein Tam Bein Muad Meshalem Nezek Shalem. You pay
the full amount. You don't even pay half, which is what you
normally pay the first three times. So as Michael says, the house
always wins. Which basically is, here's how we read the verse. Okay?
We read the verse the following: כי יגח שור איש את שור
רעהו. Ki Yigach Shor Ish Et Shor Re'ehu. When a normal person's
ox gores a normal person's ox, then you pay half the first
three times. If however, a normal person's ox gores הקדש'ס Hekdesh's ox,
then you gotta pay full. Okay, that's not... the idea of only
paying half is only a normal person's ox. If you gore הקדש'ס
Hekdesh's ox, then you gotta pay full. However, if הקדש'ס Hekdesh's ox...
it's only if a normal person's ox gores somebody else's. If הקדש'ס
Hekdesh's ox gores somebody else's, they pay nothing. Okay? So the verse
is talking about the מזיק Mazik and the ניזק Nizak are normal
people. But if הקדש Hekdesh takes either of those roles over, then
all of the benefit gets to הקדש. Hekdesh. If הקדש Hekdesh is
the מזיק, Mazik, they pay nothing. And if הקדש Hekdesh is the
ניזק, Nizak, you pay them full. Okay, so that's how רבי שמעון
בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon Ben Menasya reads the verse and that's what
רבי עקיבא... Rabbi Akiva... then you understand the קל וחומר. Kal Vachomer.
If הקדש Hekdesh is so much like, you know, given so much,
you know, privilege in that case about whether they pay at all
and how much they collect, certainly when they're collecting, they collect from
עידית, Idit, from grade A, just like a normal person collects from
grade A. If I purchase a cow and I milk it and
I drink the milk, yes, what's the implication? מעילה. Meilah. You bring
a קרבן מעילה. Korban Meilah. You have to bring a קרבן. Korban.
Yeah. Do I have to pay anything? Yeah, if you're a מזיק
Mazik the cow. So, I mean, yeah, I mean, that gets to
the question of what happens when you steal from הקדש Hekdesh and
you're מזיק הקדש. Mazik Hekdesh. So yeah, I mean, you basically have
to pay... there's an interesting question that תוספות Tosafot deals with about
whether אדם המזיק Adam HaMazik is פטור Patur by הקדש. Hekdesh. This
is talking about the שור המזיק. Shor HaMazik. Is there a special
פסוק Pasuk to exempt them? אדם המזיק Adam HaMazik or not. So
yeah, I mean, but certainly, you know, you... the basic answer is
that you pay back. Yes. So just to understand, that's just רבי
שמעון בן מנסיא's Rabbi Shimon Ben Menasya opinion, or actually is it
the opinion that הקדש Hekdesh loses? Yeah, no, the other opinion is
that הקדש Hekdesh just kind of loses in both directions. הקדש Hekdesh
doesn't pay, but doesn't get paid. No, it doesn't lose in both
directions, it's completely... you know, the other approach is that הקדש Hekdesh
is exempt from paying and exempt from being paid. Completely. Okay? But
רבי שמעון בן מנסיא Rabbi Shimon Ben Menasya says it wins in
both directions. Okay, so if you drank the milk... yeah, yeah, so
right, under those, yes. Okay, under the right circumstances, yes. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, בין לרבנן בין לרבי שמעון
בן מנסיא, Bein LeRabbanan Bein LeRabbi Shimon Ben Menasya, אי הכי, Ei
Hachi, so then he pays עידית. Idit. So now you understand הקדש
Hekdesh is so privileged in these issues, of course that when it
collects, it's going to collect from עידית. Idit. But it says one
minute: אי הכי ממאי דבעידית דניזק כי זיבורא דמזיק פליגי? Ei Hachi
Mimai DeBeIdit DeNizak Ki Zibura DeMazik Pligi? If that's true, that רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is making a point that הקדש Hekdesh collects top
quality, the גמרא Gemara says how do you know that the debate
of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael is about
whether you pay the best of the ניזק Nizak or the best
of the מזיק? Mazik? Maybe they're not debating a normal case at
all. Maybe רבי עקיבא'ס Rabbi Akiva's whole debate is about what the
הקדש Hekdesh story is. Okay, meaning since רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva in
the end talks about הקדש, Hekdesh, maybe that's all they're talking about
is the הקדש Hekdesh issue. אי הכי ממאי דבעידית דניזק כי זיבורא
דמזיק פליגי? Ei Hachi Mimai DeBeIdit DeNizak Ki Zibura DeMazik Pligi? How
do you know they're debating this case where the ניזק Nizak has
grade C and the מזיק Mazik has grade A? דילמא דכולי עלמא
בדינא דניזק שמינא? Dilma DeKulei Alma BeDina DeNizak Shamina? Maybe everybody agrees
to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that you... that you determine it based
on the ניזק'ס Nizak's property. והכא בפלוגתא דרבי שמעון בן מנסיא ורבנן
קמיפלגי. VeHacha BiPlugta DeRabbi Shimon Ben Menasya VeRabbanan Kamifligi. Maybe they're not
debating a normal case at all. They're just debating a question about
whether הקדש Hekdesh gets to collect, do you read it like רבי
שמעון בן מנסיא? Rabbi Shimon Ben Menasya? So רבי עקיבא סבר לה
כרבי שמעון בן מנסיא, Rabbi Akiva Savar Lah KeRabbi Shimon Ben Menasya,
so הקדש Hekdesh collects and they're going to collect the best. ורבי
ישמעאל סבר לה כרבנן, VeRabbi Ishmael Savar Lah KeRabbanan, and רבי ישמעאל
Rabbi Ishmael holds like the רבנן Rabbanan that הקדש Hekdesh never collects
by damage cases. So the גמרא Gemara says no, that doesn't make
sense. אם כן מאי לא בא הכתוב אלא? Im Kein Mai Lo
Ba HaKatuv Ela? When רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says the פסוק Pasuk
is only coming to do X, he's saying that before
he... about what the best field means. ועוד מאי קל וחומר להקדש?
V'od mai kal v'chomer l'hekdesh? And you wouldn't in any way have
a קל וחומר להקדש kal v'chomer l'hekdesh because then because you know
then
again there's a little bit of debate of רש"י ותוספות Rashi and
Tosfos how to read this, but it basically means that if רבי
עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is agreeing to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that you
go by the ניזק's nizak property, that's actually not a full privilege
to go by the ניזק's nizak property. קל וחומר להקדש Kal v'chomer
l'hekdesh sounds like רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva started by saying I'm going
to give the guy more than you רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael are
giving him and then I'm also going to give it to הקדש.
hekdesh. Okay. ועוד אמר רב אשי, V'od amar Rav Ashi, רב אשי
Rav Ashi says, תניא בהדיא, tanya b'hedya, we've got an explicit ברייתא
braisa that says that this is the debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Ishmael. מיטב שדהו ומיטב כרמו ישלם. Meitav sadeihu u'meitav
karmo yeshalem. מיטב שדהו של ניזק ומיטב כרמו של ניזק דברי רבי
ישמעאל. Meitav sadeihu shel nizak u'meitav karmo shel nizak divrei Rabbi Yishmael.
It's very explicit. רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael says the best of the
fields of the ניזק. nizak. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, and
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says, מיטב שדהו של מזיק ומיטב כרמו של
מזיק. meitav sadeihu shel mazik u'meitav karmo shel mazik. No, the best
of the fields of the מזיק. mazik. Okay, so there's another interesting
question about does הקדש hekdesh collect in cases of damages and if
so it should be at least as entitled as
a normal person's ability to collect from the best of the fields.
But there is this fundamental debate of רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva and
רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael how at a תורה Torah level you assess
the best of the field. Okay, so what have we said now?
The משנה mishnah that says that we have a תיקון עולם tikun
olam that you collect the best of the מזיק's mazik field, again
not more than the value of the damage but equal to the
value of the damage you collect from the best of the מזיק's
mazik field, this is according to רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Ishmael that says
at a תורה Torah level you only collect from the best of
your fields, the ניזק's nizak field, and from a רבנן rabbanan level
they let you collect from the best of the damager's, the מזיק's.
mazik רב אשי אמר לעולם אוקימנא כרבי עקיבא. Rav Ashi amar l'olam
okimna k'Rabbi Akiva.
I'm going to get our משנה mishnah to go like רבי עקיבא.
Rabbi Akiva. Oh, isn't it already a תורה Torah law that you
go from the best of the מזיק? mazik? So he says דאמר
מדאורייתא בדמזיק שיימינן, de-amar mide-oraisa be-de-mazik shamaynan, that
you do say that it's already in the תורה. Torah. But what
does it mean it's a תיקון עולם? tikun olam? דרבי שמעון היא.
d'Rabbi Shimon hi. What it means is it's going like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon דדרש טעמא דקרא. d'darash ta'ama dikra. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
says we are entitled to try to understand what is the underlying
principle of a פסוק. pasuk. Okay, I'll get back to what that
means in a moment but let's just finish this thought. ומה טעם
קאמר, v'ma ta'am ka'amar, what it's saying is what is the reason?
Yes, it's תיקון עולם tikun olam we don't mean a דרבנן derabbanan
law here. Here we mean a תורה Torah law. But what we're
doing is we're explicating the thinking behind the תורה Torah law.
Okay. מה טעם דניזק שיימינן להו בעידית, Mah ta'am de-nizak shamaynan lehu
be-idit, why is it that the תורה Torah set the הלכה halacha
is that in cases of damages you get to collect the best
of the מזיק's mazik field? מפני
תיקון עולם mipnei tikun olam because the תורה Torah is concerned about,
is trying to do this as a form of social control of
right of the best of what's for society. Because if you think
about it if it was purely based on compensation, you damage a
grade B field of mine, you give me back a grade B
field. So, well okay, but I mean at least it's an equivalent,
right? You're totally being made whole. Your grade B field was damaged,
you get something totally equivalent, you're made whole, end of story. Why
is the תורה Torah putting a heavier burden on the מזיק? mazik?
It must be that the תורה's Torah got not just the immediate
sense of justice in mind, not just the דין din in mind,
but a תיקון עולם, tikun olam, a larger societal agenda that by
making people pay the best, that hopefully we'll get these things to
happen less often. So what we're doing is we're explicating the thinking,
right? A simple sense of תשלומין tashlumim doesn't explain it. There's a
תיקון עולם tikun olam thing going on here in the תורה Torah
and that's what we're doing. But that fits with רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon who feels that we're entitled to try to identify and explicate
what is the reason behind the פסוק. pasuk. Okay, now let's just
read a little bit more. One minute. דתניא, D'tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא. braisa. אמר רבי שמעון מפני מה, Amar Rabbi Shimon mipnei
mah, and it's the same רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon who normally is
דורש טעמא דקרא doresh ta'ama dikra and he says it here too.
מפני מה אמרו הניזקין שמין להן בעידית, Mipnei mah amru ha-nezikin shamin
lahen be-idit, why did, funny phrase, they say, of course the they
is the תורה Torah says, but maybe through the mouth of the
rabbis, why does the תורה Torah say that cases of damage is
paid from the best of the field? מפני הגזלנין ומפני החמסנין, Mipnei
ha-gazlanin u-mipnei ha-chamsanin, because of the thieves and the חמסנין chamsanin are
people that like well yeah people that like force you to sell
property. כדי שיאמר אדם, Kedei she-yomar adam, so a person should say
to himself, למה אני גוזל ולמה אני חומס, lamah ani gozel v'lamah
ani chomes, why am I going to steal, why am I going
to sort of like what's the point of engaging in these types
of activities? למחר בית דין יורדים לנכסיי ונוטלים שדה נאה שלי. Le-machar
beis din yordin l'nechasai v'notlin sadeh na'ah sheli. I'm going to actually
lose out. If I just had to pay equivalent to what I
did then there's very little to be lost. Let me go ahead
and do it. Worst case scenario I'll give it back, which is
a very hard thing to understand in the תורה, Torah, right? A
גנב ganav pays double but a גזלן gazlan
only pays equivalent. So where's the disincentive to be a גזלן? gazlan?
You'll just give it back, right? So here at least is a
disincentive that if you don't have the cash, you're going to give
back the best of your field. Okay, now the interesting thing is
וסמכו על מה שכתוב בתורה מיטב שדהו מיטב כרמו ישלם vesamchu al
mah shekatuv baTorah meitav sadehu meitav karmo yeshalem and then בית דין
Beit Din will rely on what's- now what's set in the- by
the way, this phrase "they will rely on," what does it mean
they'll rely on what's in the Torah? It is what's in the
Torah. So this might also explain his phrase about why did they
say מיטב? meitav? Because the Torah only says מיטב שדהו meitav sadehu
in the case where an animal goes and grazes in another animal's
field, right? כי ישלב יבעיר ביער בשדה אחר מיטב שדהו מיטב כרמו
ישלם. ki yeshalev yaveer biyer bisedeh acher meitav sadehu meitav karmo yeshalem.
It doesn't say it in the case of stealing. It doesn't say
it in the case of, you know, other forms of seizing property.
Only says it in one case. חז"ל Chazal from a גזירה שוה
gezeirah shavah which you would learn- we'll learn when we get to
בבא קמא, Bava Kamma, applies this to all cases of damages. So
that is a rabbinic interpretation. So now you understand the ממאי אמרו
mimmay amru in the plural? Why did they say? And they'll rely
on- they're using this פסוק pasuk to apply it across the board,
okay, to all cases of- well it is מן התורה. min haTorah.
It's a דרש מן התורה, drash min haTorah, like most of, you
know, most
of תורה שבעל פה, Torah she'be'al peh, right, all דאורייתא. De'oraita. I
once- I once had a student who said, "Okay, it's דאורייתא, Doraisa,
but it's not biblical."
Which basically is right. דאורייתא Doraisa means the way the Rabbis interpret
what Torah law is. Okay. Anyway, לפיכך אמרו, lefichach amru, okay, לפיכך
אמרו הנזיקין שמין להם בעידית. lefichach amru hanizikin shamin lahem be'idit. That's
why again they said, that the נזיקין nizikin goes בעידית. be'idit. Okay.
Now, before we get on, now we're going to go and explicate
the rest of the משנה. Mishnah. But basically what we said is,
yes, it's דאורייתא, Doraisa, but it's explaining the reasoning behind the Torah.
Okay. And the Torah is doing it not just as an issue
of justice and compensation, but as a way of disincentive and a
larger societal goal. But not only by the way, it is a
little bit of a קל וחומר. kal vachomer. If the Torah makes
me pay the best of my fields when I'm just negligent and
I let my animals go out and graze, and that's the תיקון
עולם tikkun olam that the Torah is imposing there, then how much
more so should that apply when I'm willfully damaging or stealing from
your property? Just one- okay. Now Tosafot question about רבי שמעון דורש
טעמא דקרא. Rabbi Shimon doresh ta'ama de'kra. What's special about רבי שמעון?
Rabbi Shimon? I mean, you know, I mean the idea of טעמי
המצוות ta'amei hamitzvot is a big endeavor, we do it all the
time, right? Like you look at רמב"ם. Rambam. So the חידוש chiddush
of רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is that he's willing to speculate on
what is the reason behind the מצוה mitzvah and then use it
to determine the parameters of what the מצוה mitzvah is. Not just-
not just to סתם stam talk about what the reasons are. So
look at תוספות. Tosafot. רבי שמעון דהוה דורש טעמא דקרא, Rabbi Shimon
dehavah doresh ta'ama de'kra, לא פליגי lo pligi says תוספות, Tosafot, אלא
היכא דאיכא נפקותא. ela heicha de'ika nafkusa. Only if there's some application
to this, you're going to say the reason and then you're going
to apply it to determine the parameters of the דין. din. כגון
גבי חובל בגד אלמנה, kegon gabei chovel beged almanah, וגבי לא ירבה
לו נשים. vegabei lo yarbeh lo nashim. Okay. So basically
the Torah says לא תחבול בגד אלמנה. lo tachbol beged almanah. What
if- what if the widow is rich? So רבי ישמעאל Rabbi Yishmael
says oh it doesn't apply in a case where the widow is
rich. Okay, רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, for he's דורשינא טעמא דקרא. dorshina
ta'ama de'kra. Now you and I would think that טעמא דקרא ta'ama
de'kra that he's he's sort of suggesting or assuming is that it's
a way of like taking advantage of the poor, oppressing the poor,
so it doesn't apply if the- if the widow happens to be
rich. He actually gives- this just shows you how widely variant טעמא
דקרא ta'ama de'kra could be when you try to speculate what the
reason is. So he says no, you know what the טעמא דקרא
ta'ama de'kra is? If it's a poor person's garment, the Torah says
you have to return it every day. So if you're- this is
a widow, no man is at home, you're returning her garment every
single day, you're visiting her house every single day, it's going to
raise suspicions about, you know, sexual impropriety. But if she's a rich
widow, you don't have an obligation to return it. Anyway, completely bizarre,
nothing we would have assumed would have been the reason behind it.
But anyway, he's willing to use it to explain the parameters of
the דין. din. Now how does that apply here? Here, how is
it determining the parameters? It's just what the Torah says, מיטב שדהו.
meitav sadehu. Why are we limiting this to רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon?
Why- you know, where- where here is he using the reason to
determine the parameters? So let's look at the next lines of תוספות.
Tosafot. הכא נמי משום האי טעמא שיימינן בעידית. hacha nami mishum hai
ta'ama shayminan be'idit. Now what does תוספות Tosafot mean? Meaning that's- where-
right? Where is this רבי שמעון? Rabbi Shimon? Right? Where is he
getting that from? I mean what's- what's רבי שמעון's טעמא דקרא Rabbi
Shimon's ta'ama de'kra doing to tell me anything that I don't already
know from the
פסוק? pasuk? And that's my question. So I would suggest two things.
Number one is תוספות Tosafot is saying maybe that's what's pushing רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon to read the פסוק pasuk like רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva and not like רבי ישמעאל. Rabbi Yishmael. If you see it
as a תיקון עולם, tikkun olam, you're going to read it like
that we're going to be like- going to be more strict on
the penalty and we're going to do it the best of the
מזיק, mazik, not the best of the ניזק. nizak. But I think
that's what תוספות Tosafot is getting at. But the other thing I
would say is the point that I was making before, that the
Torah only applies it to the case of grazing in somebody else's
field. It doesn't apply to all cases of damages.
What motivates the rabbis to read the פסוק pasuk by this narrow
case of an animal grazing in a field... and interpret it by
all cases of damages, you pay the best. So the reason is,
well, if you understand the reason behind this is תיקון עולם, Tikkun
Olam, then you'll say what I just said. Well, if the תורה
Torah is doing the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam by mere negligence, how
much more so should we assume that this principle applies in cases
where it's like willful damage, right? And so that seems to be
the point, that this is a, so yes, it's in the תורה,
Torah, but by saying it's תיקון עולם, Tikkun Olam, we're identifying what
we assume is the reason behind it in the תורה, Torah, and
that's also what's entitling us to read the פסוק pasuk and to
apply it across the board to all cases of damages, like רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says. Why did they say? They relied on that
פסוק pasuk in order to read it to apply to all cases
of damages. Dov, you had a question. Yeah, so, it's clear that
this whole argument is developmental with layers, right? It's not the פשט
peshat of the משנה. Mishnah. Like the first two cases of the
רישא Reisha of the משנה Mishnah is נזק nezek and then loans.
Right. It doesn't say those are because of תיקון עולם. Tikkun Olam.
Then כתובת אשה ketubat isha is thrown into
that set because of תיקון עולם, Tikkun Olam, and then a מציאה.
metziah. Because otherwise, it could just be a מחלוקת machloket on how
to דרש darshan the פסוק. pasuk. It could be that the first
part of the משנה Mishnah is just laying the background to get
to the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam in the end, but the first
thing that the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam is said is not about
any of the grade A, grade B, grade C. So the first
thing it's said on is about
collecting אכילת פירות achilat peirot from,
you don't collect it from נכסים משועבדים. nechasim meshubadim. So תיקון עולם
Tikkun Olam is only going on the thing that it's directly
juxtaposed to it, and it's not relevant to the first half of
the משנה Mishnah at all. There's no need to even teach the
first half. Now you could say אין הכי נמי, ein hachi nami,
it's all a lead-in to the last point, but that's not how
the גמרא Gemara reads it. The גמרא Gemara reads תיקון עולם Tikkun
Olam as referring to, right, reading to apply to the whole משנה.
Mishnah. That is correct. Okay, מלווה על פה לא גובה? Malveh al
peh lo goveh? I don't remember. Anyway, so now the גמרא Gemara
says like this. So now that we're dealing with רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon explaining the מפני מה אמרו, mipnei mah amru, so we dealt
with the first one, which now really you're understanding is why חז"ל
Chazal read the פסוק pasuk that way, or applied the פסוק's pasuk's
case of שן ורגל shen v'regel and applied it to all cases
of נזק, nezek, because they understood that it was a תיקון עולם
Tikkun Olam type of a thing that the תורה Torah was saying.
And now we're going to continue to explain the משנה Mishnah based
on what is the תיקון עולם Tikkun Olam at each stage of
the משנה. Mishnah. So let's keep on going. Okay, מפני מה אמרו
בחוב בבינונית? mipnei mah amru be-chov be-veinonit? Now why did the Rabbis,
this is still רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon talking, say that a creditor
collects middle grade? כדי שלא יראה אדם לחברו שדה נאה ודירה נאה,
kedei she-lo yireh adam le-chavero sadeh na'ah v'dirah na'ah, a person shouldn't
say that guy's got a nice field, he's got a beautiful house,
ויאמר אקפוץ ואלוונו כדי שאגבנו בחובי. v'yomar ekpotz v'alvenu kedei she-agvenu be-chovi.
You know what? Let me lend him money, he'll probably default, and
it'll give me a great opportunity to take over his house, to
take his house. Okay, predatory lending. So there you go. So לפיכך
אמרו בחוב בבינונית. lefikach amru be-chov be-veinonit. They said that no, you
collect middle grade so that you don't use it as an opportunity
to seize the guy's best property. The גמרא Gemara says אלא מעתה
יהא בזיבורית. ela me'ata yehei be-ziborit. So let's say that he only
gets grade C, so he shouldn't use it as an opportunity to
get the grade B property. No, אם כן אתה נועל דלת בפני
לווין. im ken atah no'el delet bifnei lovin. No, everything comes at
a cost, right? Every type of thing you do, there's another side
to the equation, right? So therefore,
if you do that, nobody wants to lend money. In general, you
really do need to incentivize people to lend money in the תורה.
Torah. They don't collect interest, loans get annulled after seven years, you
know, when the שמיטה shemitah rolls around, so it's really like it's
a loser's deal to lend money. They might, even if none of
that happens, you might not be able to recollect the debt, the
guy might default, right? That's why the תורה Torah frames, by the
way, it's interesting to know, the basic idea of צדקה, tzedakah, a
straight gift of money, is basically not in the תורה. Torah. I
challenge you to find me a case in the תורה Torah where
the תורה Torah says that if somebody asks for money, you give
them money as a gift.
פתוח תפתח. patuach tiftach. Yeah, פתוח תפתח את ידך לו והעבט תעביטנו.
patuach tiftach et yadcha lo v'ha'aveit ta'avitenu.
העבט תעביטנו ha'aveit ta'avitenu and עבות avot is give him a loan.
Okay, because עבות avot is a collateral. And that פסוק pasuk talks
about how the שמיטה shemitah will come and annul the loan. All
the פסוקים psukim that are quoted about giving money are פסוקים psukim
about giving loans. The only thing
the תורה Torah talks, actually it says, the only time the תורה
Torah has a case of giving something as a straight gift is
תרומות ומעשרות trumot u'ma'asrot or לקט שכחה ופאה, leket shikcha u'peah, okay?
Okay, but in terms of like putting your hand in your pocket,
somebody asks for money, it's all about a loan. Loan in the
תורה Torah is a form of צדקה, tzedakah, because a loan, you
don't charge interest, it gets annulled after seven years, it gets forgiven.
Okay, so you really got to incentivize people to give loans. So
this is not much of an incentive, but we can't go, but
we're not going to make it, like, disincentivize people even more. So
we have to at least let the creditor collect the grade B.
We can't collect grade A because then it'll lead to taking advantage,
but we cannot say grade C because then. That'll make nobody's going
to want to lend money then. We just had a whole פרק
Perek that discussed or a whole major section that discussed, you know,
פרוזבול, Pruzbul, what we have to do to get people to keep
on lending money within this type of context. Yes, Charlie. I was
going to say, and then later on when we stop being agricultural,
the Rabbis developed the היתר עסקא. Heter Iska. Right, exactly. But that's
correct. So that also helps give helps people have a reason to
lend money. Okay. Now, כתובת אשה בזיבורית, Kesubas Isha biziboris, דברי רבי
יהודה. divrei Rabbi Yehuda. Now
let's talk about the כתובת אשה, Kesubas Isha, what's it collect on
there? The woman is collecting the worst of the property. That's יהודה.
Yehuda. רבי מאיר אומר בבינונית, Rabbi Meir omer bebinonis, middle property. אמר
רבי שמעון, Amar Rabbi Shimon, מפני מה אמרו כתובת אשה בזיבורית? mipnei
mah amru Kesubas Isha biziboris? Comes along רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon again,
the same way he's דורשין טעמא דקרא, dorshin ta'ama dikra, he's דורשין
טעמא דרבנן. dorshin ta'ama derabbanan. Okay? He comes to explain to us
what the reasons are. So why did they say a woman would
collect, if a woman collects grade B, that's like any other creditor,
right? They collect middle grade. But what's the logic of collecting grade
C? שיותר ממה שאיש רוצה לישא אשה רוצה להינשא. Sheyoser mi-mah she-ish
rotzeh liso isha rotzah lihinasay. Men,
women are more eager to get married than men. You've got to
incentivize the men to get married. So a way to say this
a little softer is, is that women are already given all this
financial protection through חז"ל Chazal through the כתובה, Kesubah, right? The כתובה
Kesubah gives her financial protection if she gets divorced or widowed. It
actually gives her ongoing financial protection in the marriage. Okay, it's not
our idea of a sort of of an equal types of rights
and responsibilities, that wasn't the reality in those times, but it was
definitely a tremendous innovation to protect her in all these different ways.
Alright, but you can't make it so much that she's getting to
protect her that it's going to disincentivize men or make men, you
know, wait a few years more before getting married. We have a
big enough problem right now right about people getting married at too
late at, you know, at a later age and so on. So
therefore what we have to do is we have to make it
more feasible for a person willing to assume this type of a
debt. Fine, I'll assume the debt, but it's not going to be
from my best property or my even my grade B, it'll be
from my grade C. So that we have to do is to
make it easier for men to get married. Okay, דבר אחר, davar
acher, now here's another explanation, which says which is going to be
bizarre. אשה יוצאה לרצונה ושלא לרצונה, Isha yotzah lirtsonah veshelo lirtsonah, a
woman can get divorced whether she wants it or not wants it,
she's divorced against can be divorced against her will. ואיש אינו מוציא
אלא לרצונו, Ve-ish eino motsia ela lirtsono,
but a man only divorces his wife willingly. Now, whatever that's that's
very unclear what that has to do with anything, but what certainly
it says is that the woman is disadvantaged in issues of divorce,
if anything that means we should be protecting her more, not less.
So how is that relevant? So the גמרא Gemara says מאי דבר
אחר? mai davar acher? How is this relevant? וכי תימא Vekhi teima
כי היכי דמפיק לה איהו ki heichi d'mappik lah ihu דתיקנו לה
רבנן כתובה מיניה. dakinu lah rabanan kesubah mineih.
One minute. As long as we're talking about תיקון עולם, tikkun olam,
so why don't we say, and we did this actually, and we
actually said it's זיבורית ziboris because we were concerned about his interests.
So you're telling me תיקון עולם tikkun olam and we're talking about
being concerned about the husband's interests. Well wait a minute, I'm here
from the, you know, from the Men's Rights Movement and I'm saying,
if you're concerned about the man's interests, then when the same way
she gets a כתובה kesubah when he is divorcing her, he should
get a כתובה kesubah when she's divorcing him. Except what? Okay, so
כי נפקא איהי נמי ליתקנו לה רבנן כתובה מינה. ki nafka ihi
nami letiknu lah rabanan kesubah minah.
So when he's the one being the divorced, he should collect a
כתובה, kesubah, which is the most absurd הוה אמינא, hava amina, where
have you been through all of מסכת גיטין? Maseches Gittin? Okay. So
the גמרא Gemara says, תא שמע, ta shema, אשה יוצאה לרצונה ושלא
לרצונה ואיש אינו מוציא אלא לרצונו. isha yotzah lirtsonah veshelo lirtsonah ve-ish
eino motsia ela lirtsono. No,
a man cannot be divorced against his will. He only divorces if
he's the one willing to, he's the one initiating the divorce, he's
the one that has to provide the wife a כתובה, kesubah, not
the other way around. אפשר דמשלי לה בגיטה Efshar d'mashli lah begitta
and if he doesn't, you know, he can withhold a גט, get,
very funny then not funny, whatever, sad that's already recognized there. Okay,
it's totally his choice if he wants to give her a גט
get or not give her
a גט. get. She doesn't get to be the one to decide
about whether they're getting divorced or not. So it's a crazy הוה
אמינא, hava amina, right? Like what even הוה אמינא hava amina is
it? Most you could say maybe it means was, let's say she's
the cause of the divorce. Let's say she's doing things to make
his life miserable to force, you know, to try to force a
divorce, at least in that case why shouldn't he be, now I
don't know how you would prove that, but in the end the
גמרא Gemara says none of that really matters. He's still the one
that gets to decide, so he's still the one that pays the
כתובה kesubah not the other way around. The other point though is
is that it really is like a little bit irrespective of who's
the one initiating the divorce, right? Like in, you know, if you
think about, you know, before when we were basically one-income families and
the husband was the prime wage earner, whether he initiated the divorce
proceedings or the wife initiated the divorce proceedings, she was entitled to
alimony because she had basically been keeping up the home and had
the, you know, and he had the one earning the wages, so
she was entitled to protection and to, you know, and to financial
protection. So it really that's also funny, it's not like because you
did it you have to pay her. There's a difference here
and
is the bottom line is they're unwilling to have the woman incur
debt, no matter how you could structure the argument. Right. So the
bottom line is she's going to be protected by not being the
one to incur any debt as a result of the divorce. Correct.
I'm just saying that the הוה אמינא Hava Amina was first of
all, it's a bizarre הוה אמינא. Hava Amina. All of a sudden
we think that the woman can divorce the man? Okay, so maybe
you read it that she could like he would like, you know,
he would make his life miserable and try to force him to
divorce. But even so, the fact that the payment of a כתובה
Kesuvah is based on who's giving the divorce and not based on
the financial realities, right, is strange. You know, yes. The extension to
contemporary times where the woman is the wage earner. Right. So what
you're saying about, you know, in terms of the כתובה. Kesuvah. So
the כתובה Kesuvah basically entitles the man to the woman's earnings in
exchange for him providing...
providing support, like, you know, room and board. But since it was
done to protect the woman's interest, she's in a position to say,
I waive the room and support and I'm keeping my earnings, because
it's all done to protect her interests, not his. So in modern
times, if basically... I mean we, you know, we don't actually here
in the States, Israel's maybe a different question, we don't really like
divide our family's finances based on the כתובה. Kesuvah. But were we
to do that, and it would be disadvantageous to the woman to
follow the rules of the כתובה, Kesuvah, she could waive it. It's
done to protect her. As far as we go. In other words,
we don't say because she's the wage earner that he should
be paid. Oh, right, meaning yes. Meaning going back to my point
that basically it was who was bringing in the money. Right, look,
you could imagine a case that a woman came from a wealthy
family, the man was a pauper, and so even there in this
particular circumstance where the finances were reversed, we weren't going to switch
around the כתובה. Kesuvah. That's true. So maybe, you know, maybe that's
partly what the גמרא Gemara is saying, that it's also based on
the question of who's divorcing whom, right? I'm sorry. So what are
we trying to say about this דבר אחר? davar acher? I don't
know, it's a complete digression. תוספות Tosafot tries to make it relevant
to the question of זיבורית, ziboris, but it seems like a complete
digression. It's like if you're telling me זיבורית ziboris is because we
care about the man's interest and we're trying to protect his interest
in the marriage, why don't we protect it more? Why don't we
give him a כתובה? Kesuvah? And the answer is that's absurd. Yes.
Is there any discussion about how this changes for the חרם דרבינו
גרשום? Cherem de-Rabbeinu Gershom? No, not here. I mean, no, but I
mean basically כתובה Kesuvah is still... right, because in the end that's
not what כתובה Kesuvah is about. And anyway, okay. כתובת אשה בזיבורית.
Kesuvas Ishah bi-ziboris. Now, let's get to look at this debate. Okay,
so that... we've just completely leapfrogged over the ברייתא, Baraisa, we've addressed
what we wanted to say about that, balancing, you know, not predatory
lending as opposed to
not disincentivizing a loan. And now we focus on the כתובה. Kesuvah.
אמר מר זוטרא בריה דרב נחמן, Amar Mar Zutra breih de-Rav Nachman,
לא אמרו אלא מיתמי. Lo amru ela mi-yasmi. It's only when she's
collecting from the orphans that because in order to protect the interests
of the orphans we say it has to be זיבורית. ziboris. Okay,
אבל מיניה דידיה, aval minei didei,
but if she's collecting from the husband, it's a case of divorce,
not of debt, so בינונית. beinonis. So she's like a creditor, right?
Why should she be less... have a less advantage than a normal
creditor? So the גמרא Gemara says one minute. מיתמי, mi-yasmi, if they're
only debating the case of orphans, so מאי איריא כתובת אשה? mai
irya Kesuvas Ishah? Then why
is it only a כתובה Kesuvah that
is being singled out as that it's from the grade C? אפילו
כל מילי נמי, afillu kol milli nami, all things from orphans are
grade C, דהא תנן, de-ha tnan, our משנה Mishnah says, אין נפרעין
מנכסי יתומים אלא מזיבורית. ein nifrain mi-nichsei yesomim ela mi-ziboris. So the
fact that we say כתובה Kesuvah is מן הזיבורית min ha-ziboris seems
to be independent of the orphan factor. So the גמרא Gemara says
אלא לאו מיניה, ela lav minei, it must be that when we're
talking about the כתובה Kesuvah debate whether it's grade C or grade
B, we're talking about from him. The גמרא Gemara says no, לעולם
מיתמי, le-olam mi-yasmi, we are talking about orphans. וכתובת אשה איצטריכא ליה.
ve-Kesuvas Ishah itztericha lei. When we say the כתובה Kesuvah is from
grade C, the point is even the כתובה Kesuvah is grade C
when you're collecting from orphans. סלקא דעתך אמינא, salka daitach amina, משום
חינא, mishum china, אקילו רבנן גביה. akilu Rabbanan gabei. So משום חינא
mishum china is like the opposite argument about trying to incentivize the
man. It's that משום חינא mishum china is like we have to...
well there's a debate of רש״י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot how to
read it. רש״י Rashi reads it as we also have to incentivize
the woman. If we disadvantage the woman too much by a כתובה,
Kesuvah, she's not going to want to get married. Okay, תוספות Tosafot
says one minute. You can't one minute say we have to do
things to incentivize
the man and the other minute you say we have to do
things to incentivize the woman. I don't know why. Sometimes both realities
are true. But תוספות Tosafot says משום חינא mishum china is the
opposite. It's a little ironic, but what תוספות Tosafot says is the
following. This is part of incentivizing the men. If they see that
women are being given too much... are too much disadvantaged in court,
even when it means collecting from men, from husbands, but if women
are too disadvantaged in the system, then they'll lose social status in
the eyes of men and they'll say why should I, you know,
whatever, women are like... they'll treat women too much like, you know,
without respect and they won't want to get married as much because
they're mistreated by the system. It's actually interesting the way תוספות Tosafot
reads it. So if women are always collecting from the worst... property,
that actually creates a disincentive for men to get married because it's
they're not just thinking financially, they're thinking about the status that women
have in society. So sometimes we have to actually do things to
give women greater status and greater rights even against men's property, right,
in order to that that their social status not, you know, be,
you know, be of a certain position, and that ultimately is part
of incentivizing men. It's very interesting. Exactly. High enough that I want
to marry a woman, okay, that it's חשיב chashiv to me to
marry such to marry a woman, but not so high that I'm
seriously disadvantaged by it. Exactly. Okay, so anyway, so I might think
that we do this for, you know, we give her this special
privilege and that even when she's collecting from יתומים, yetomim, she's entitled
to collect grade B משום חינא, mishum china, קא משמע לן ka
mashma lan that we don't. So this is saying that actually a
normal case of כתובה ketubah is grade B, when we say כתובה's
ketubah grade C it's only from orphans, and even though everybody is
grade C from orphans, even a כתובה, ketubah, even though we might
have done something to raise a woman's status. Okay, אמר רבא תא
שמע, amar Rava ta shma,
so let's see if we can hold sustain this interpretation. רבי מאיר
אומר כתובת אישה בבינונית. Rabbi Meir omer ketubat isha be-veinonit. No, but
we see it's debated whether כתובה ketubah is grade B or grade
C. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's grade B. ממאי? mimai? Now
who are we talking about that she's collecting from? אילימא מיתמי, eilima
mi-yatmei, if she's collecting from orphans, לית ליה לרבי מאיר הא דתניא
אין נפרעין מנכסי יתומים אלא מן הזיבורית? leit lei le-Rabbi Meir ha
de-tanya ein nifra'in mi-nichsei yetomim ela min ha-ziborit? How can רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir say, if we're talking about orphans, how could he say
that you collect grade B? Orphans is grade C. אלא מיניה, ela
mineih, obviously we're talking about collecting from the husband. So the גמרא
Gemara says מכלל דרבנן סברי בזיבורית? michlal de-Rabbanan savri be-ziborit? So you
see when the rabbis say grade C, we're talking about the husband.
Since רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir grade B is obviously the husband's, then
the debate of grade B or grade C is about collecting from
the husband. So the גמרא Gemara says no, לעולם מיתמי, le-olam mi-yatmei,
we're collecting from the orphans.
So how is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir saying grade B for the
reason we said, ושאני כתובת אישה משום חינא? ve-shani ketubat isha mishum
china? Because maybe the woman has special privileges collecting the כתובה, ketubah,
the exact opposite. So now what we're arguing is, you until now
were saying that a כתובה ketubah is a disadvantage for the woman
and she goes down to grade C when she's collecting from the
husband. I refuse that. When she's collecting from the husband, grade B.
The question is, does she get a more of an advantage when
she's collecting from orphans? Okay, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says I'm
going to give a כתובה ketubah more of an advantage than a
normal creditor and the רבנן Rabbanan say no. Alright, תא שמע ta
shma again. Certainly not פשט, pshat, but let's see if where we're
go with this. אמר אביי תא שמע, amar Abaye ta shma, הנזיקין
שמין להם בעידית ובעל חוב בבינונית וכתובת אישה בזיבורית. ha-nezikin shamin lahem
be-idit u-va'al chov be-veinonit ve-ketubat isha be-ziborit. Our משנה, mishna,
it lays out these three things, right? Damages grade A, debts grade
B, כתובה ketubah grade C. ממאי? mimai? Now presumably we're all talking
about collecting from the same type of person. אילימא מיתמי, eilima mi-yatmei,
if we're talking about collecting these things from orphans, מאי אריא כתובת
אישה אפילו כולהו נמי? mai arya ketubat isha afilu kulhu nami? So
then why do we say that כתובת אישה's ketubat isha grade C?
Everybody! The creditor is grade C, the damagee is grade C. If
we're talking about orphans, everybody is grade C. So clearly when the
משנה mishna talks about the creditor being grade B and the damagee
being grade A, we're talking about collecting from the normal guy. Or
not his children. Not his children. Right, if it was his children
they'd all be grade C. So obviously we're talking about the guy
himself. So the same as when we're talking about the כתובה. ketubah.
So when you lend money make sure the guy has a long
life expectancy. אלא לאו מיניה, ela lav mineih,
we're talking about from him. אמר רב אחא בר יעקב amar Rav
Acha bar Yaakov and therefore כתובה ketubah as well. אמר רב אחא
בר יעקב, amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, הכא במאי עסקינן, hacha be-mai
askinan, כגון שנעשה ערב לנזקי בנו ולבעל חוב בנו ולכתובת כלתו. kegon
she-na'asa arev le-nizkei bno u-le-va'al chov bno u-le-ketubat kalato. So
certainly totally not פשט, pshat, but what we're going to talking about
here is a case which is neither orphans nor the guy himself.
What would be a case that's neither orphans nor the guy himself?
Basically somebody agreed to be a guarantor of the loan. I will
be a guarantor of any damages that your animals inflict or I'll
be a guarantor of your normal loan or I'll be a guarantor
for my
son to pay off his כתובה. ketubah. Okay, and then all these
people come to me. Okay, so if it's a בעל חוב, ba'al
chov, he gets my grade B. If it's a נזק, nezek, he
gets my grade A, the same way the actual person himself. If
it's a כתובת אישה, ketubat isha, now we can explain why it's
grade C. Because what we're saying is is that the כתובת אישה,
ketubat isha, this is like our compromise because we have to concede
that there's cases where כתובת אישה's ketubat isha grade C that isn't
orphans. Everybody is grade C with orphans. So if it's a third
party, it's an ערב, arev, as long as it's if the guy
himself, we're going to say it's grade B that you pay your
wife for כתובה. ketubah. But if it's an ערב, arev, that's where
it's going to be grade C. Okay, והא ve-ha and now why
is that? Why do we say that if everybody else you pay
what they would have paid, right, grade A and grade B, so
when you come to if I'm a guarantor for my son for
his כתובה, ketubah, then if the wife is coming to me I
should be paying grade B. Why in
that case would I go and pay grade C? Is that clear
what I'm describing here? Yes? Okay. So let's take a look. So
the גמרא Gemara says, והאי כדיניה והאי כדיניה. Vehay k'dinay vehay k'dinay.
Everybody pays according to what their normal law would be. נזיקין ובעל
חוב דמחיים גבו, Nezikin u-baal chov d'mechayim gavu, איהו נמי כי גבי
מחיים מגבי. ihu nami ki gavi mechayim magbi. So נזיקין ובעל חוב
Nezikin u-baal chov normally are collected when the people are alive. So
when you go to the guarantor, you collect as if you'd be
doing a normal collection. What's a normal collection of a case of
a בעל חוב baal chov or whatever, a normal collection is grade
A or grade B. The normal collection is when they're alive. כתובת
אשה דלאחר מיתה גביא, Kesuvas isha d'le'achar misa gavia, אבל בכתובה, aval
b'kesuva, when
it is often collected, or maybe we'd say standard collection, maybe we
assume death, the husband dies before the wife in 50% of the
cases, right? Let's just assume whatever, I probably more because women have
longer life ex- well, I don't know, in that day they had
less, whatever. Anyway, whatever. But divorce happens a lot less than death.
Okay. So a standard כתובה kesuva is collected after death.
So here when it's collected from not the husband himself but from
the ערב, areiv, it's collected as a normal collection of a כתובה,
kesuva, and a normal collection of a כתובה kesuva is seen to
be a collection from orphans and a grade C collection. Okay. כתובת
אשה דלאחר מיתה גביא, Kesuvas isha d'le'achar misa gavia, ולאחר מיתה ממאן
גביא, u'le'achar misa miman gavia, who are you collecting after death? מיתמי.
mi'yasmi. איהו נמי כי גבי כלאחר מיתה מגבי. Ihu nami ki gavi
k'le'achar misa magbi. He is collecting like it's after death. So it's
a very
convoluted way of reading the משנה. mishna. Okay. Basically we're going to
try to say כתובת אשה kesuvas isha is grade C only when
it's from orphans. Clearly the beginning of the משנה mishna is not
talking about orphans, but what we do is we construct a case
that it's talking about a guarantor. So guarantor, you're collecting like you
would normally collect, grade A or grade B. The one thing that
switches is when you're collecting actually the כתובה, kesuva, because then you
collect the way a כתובה kesuva is normally collected since you're not
actually collecting directly from the husband, you're collecting the way it's normally
collected, and that's defined as collecting grade C, and that's how it
explains the משנה. mishna. The rabbis want to limit the times when
the woman actually is going to collect from the least valuable property.
You want to- right, that's the way this סוגיא sugya is going.
So this סוגיא sugya is going in that direction. Right. To make
it as small as possible even the language of the משנה mishna
that she should collect from the least valuable property of the assets.
Right. Right. Now I do want to say I explained it even
assuming that the person owing the money was alive and you're going
to the guarantor. רש״י Rashi actually says that we're talking about the
person owing the money is dead. Okay, but even though the person
is dead, in the case of the loan and of the נזק,
nezek, you were entitled to collect from him before he died. So
when you're collecting from the guarantor, you're collecting based- that you were
entitled to collect when the guy was still alive and therefore you
still collect grade A and grade B. It actually explains the גמרא
Gemara much better. But the case of the כתובה, kesuva, you only
became entitled to collect because he died, right? So if the case
is that the actual guy owes the money died, so even though
you're going to the ערב, areiv, to the guarantor, you're only collecting
grade C because you're only entitled to collect because he died, and
that scenario entitles you to grade C, right? When the guy dies
and the wife collects the כתובה, kesuva, she's entitled to grade C.
So in the first two cases the person was entitled to collect
grade A and grade B, the guy dies, he went to the
ערב. areiv. The third case the woman- the guy was entitled to
collect grade- she was only entitled to collect because the husband died,
that entitled her to grade C and therefore even when she's going
to the ערב areiv she also only collects grade C. Okay, and
if she's divorced and he's obviously still alive, then how does it
work? Then she might- she might collect grade B. Exactly.
According to this approach. Okay. Well whatever, we're not done, let me
just read, I know it's late, but give me one more minute,
just read one more line. גמרא Gemara says like this, just to
finish the thought: ותיפוק ליה דערב דכתובה לא משתעבד. V'teipok lei d'areiv
d'kesuva lo mishtabed. The גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
normally guarantor doesn't work for כתובה kesuva issues, because- I don't have
to worry about why not, but basically because no money changed hands,
so the person really doesn't accept- assume the obligation by כתובה. kesuva.
גמרא Gemara says: בקבלן. B'kablan.
A special case of a קבלן kablan where basically money does change
hands and
therefore he took the money and gave it back and therefore he
does obligate himself. So the גמרא Gemara says: הניחא למאן דאמר קבלן
אף על גב דלית ליה נכסי ללווה משתעבד. Hani-cha l'man d'amar kablan
af al gav d'leisa lei nichsei l'loveh mishtabed. You know what? Let's
just end here because I have to take this call. Okay, we'll
end here.